Finding Aid for the Lloyd E. Cotsen Cuneiform Tablets Collection LSC.1883
UCLA Library Special Collections
- School text, literary exercise from Schooldays., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-IV-6; Obverse 1. 'Schoolboy, (where did you go?)' 2. 'I went to school.' 3. 'What did you do at school?' 4. 'I read my tablet. 5. I ate my lunch. 6. I made my tablet, wrote it and finished it. 7. My lines were prepared for me. 8. In the afternoon, my … were prepared for me. 9. When school ended, 10. I went home. 11. I entered the house. 12. My father was sitting there. Reverse 1. My father …; 2. I read my tablet. 3. My father was happy. 4. I found favor with my father. 5. (I said) I am thirsty, bring me drink. 6. I am hungry. Bring me food. 7. Wash my feet. 8. Set up the bed. 9. At dawn (I will awake).'; 2 1/2" height x 2 1/8" width x 1 1/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Misshapen rectangular tablet that appears to have been pressed down on one edge. Possibly due to this pressing, this edge is diagonal and much wider than its opposing edge. The clay also bulges out on two faces near this edge, as well as on an adjacent edge. There is an incomplete crack on a bulge on one face. The surface of the pressed edge is slightly rough and there is some evidence of spalling. There is another corner that also appears to have been pressed down, but much less so than the other pressed edge. There is also a scrape mark near this corner on one of the faces. It is unclear if this mark was made while the clay was still wet or after the clay had dried. There are some white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 3)
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names beginning with "lu2"., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-II-13; 2 5/8" height x 1 15/16" width x 5/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Both faces of the tablet were partially wiped smooth while the clay was wet; one face only has inscription in one corner. The face with more writing has lost a small chip in one corner. This face is a lighter color than the opposite face, which is almost black over much of its surface. The face with little writing has a small piece of white fiberous material attached in one corner. This face also has some white powdery material at the opposite end from the fiberous material. The white material is shiny like salt, but it does not appear crystalline in structure. (Drawer 4)
  This basic student exercise is practice writing personal names that begin with "lu2". This acrographic arrangment was popular among ancient Mesopotamian vocabularies.
- School text, sign exercise., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 85; 1. A divine being; 3" height x 2 1/2" width x 1" depth, red baked rectangular tablet with the reverse effaced; A small, nearly complete tablet with one small loss to one corner. One face is incised with the same star-shaped symbol repeatedly. The reverse face is uninscribed. The tablet is well fired. (Drawer 5)
  This beginner's exercise is a practice in sign formation and sound of the AN, LI and HAL signs.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names beginning with "mu"., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 147; 1. 'The assembler'; 2. 'Benefactress'; 3. 'The seller'; 4. 'The shelterer'; 5. 'The multitude'; 6. 'The intelligent one'; 3 3/8" height x 3" width x 7/8" depth, red baked square single column tablet; A complete, almost square tablet. There is one pit-like loss on one face. The tablet is stable and appears well-fired. There is also a distortion of the eclay at one edge that appears to have happened when the clay was wet. (Drawer 6)
  This basic student exercise is practice writing personal names. This text is nearly identical to 96261.
- School text, lexical exercise from Early Dynastic Food and mathematical exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-30; Obverse Column 1 (3 lines missing) 4'. … 5'. … 6'. … 7'. n units of baked bread 8'. n units of baked bread 9'. n units of baked bread 10'. n units of baked bread 11'. n units of baked bread (remaining lines missing) Column 2 (three lines missing) 4'. Half bread 5'. A type of bread 6'. … 7'. A baked product 8'. Baked products 9'. … (remaining lines missing) Column 3 (3 lines missing) 4'. A cake 5'. Cakes 6'. … 7'. A cake 8'. A cake (remaining lines missing) Reverse (effaced); 5 5/8" height x 4 3/4" width x 1 7/8" depth, large triangular multi-column fragment; All edges of this triangular tablet fragment are uneven and jagged in some areas from losses. There are considerable losses to the surface of the two faces, partially from spalling. There are incomplete cracks overall. There are some white concretions visible overall. The tablet fragment is actively crumbling in some areas. (Drawer S2)
- School text, mathematical exercise with geometry., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-40; 6 1/2" height x 3 1/8" width x 1" depth, rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet that has broken into three pieces. Several portions of the breaks and areas surrounding the breaks have been covered with adhesive. There are some white fibers stuck in the adhesive on the break near the edge. There is a dried ball of adhesive visible along the central break, as well as a small patch of what seems to be some printed material (possibly paper based) adhered to some of the adhesive. The three pieces consist of essentially two halves (this break runs across the center of the tablet) and a portion of one of the edges. There are considerable losses near the break at the edge, as well as some losses along the other break. There is a deep gouge next to the more central break. This possibly was created by an implement, alhough it is unclear if it was created while the clay was still wet. There are several incomplete cracks overall, mostly visible by the break at the edge. There seems to be some smaller losses that have been reattached along the breaks. There are some white concretions visible throughout. (Drawer S3)
  This school exercise contains two diagrams for solving geometric problems involving Pythagoras' Theorem and the value of Pi.
- School text, lexical exercise of types of beer., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); 31719.13; 1. Beer bread 2. Moist beer bread; 2 7/8" diameter x 3/4" depth, lentil with an adhesive label attached and the reverse inscribed and worn; A lenticular tablet of light brown-gray clay. There is a loss along the edge, primarily to the more convex, uninscribed face. The loss is approximately 1 3/4-inches long. There is an incomplete crack that penetrates from one face to the other but has not spread across the diameter of the tablet. The uninscribed face has a scattering of white accretions, probably salt crystals. In one area the white material is deposited under a small crack and appears to be in the process of causing spalling. There is a small, square white paper label adhered to the uninscribed side that reads, "13". (Drawer 1)
  This brief exercise is a student's vocabulary practice in writing types of beer, a popular commodity in ancient Mesopotamia.
- School text, literary exercise from Lipit-Eshtar B., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-9; 1. The foundations of his throne 2. He made firm for you, 3. On the orders 4. of An and Enlil.; 3 1/2" diameter x 7/8" depth, baked lentil joined from fragments; Lenticular tablet broken approximately in half, with the two pieces reattached with an adhesive. There is another complete crack near the edge. There is an incomplete crack on the face with cuneiform impressions that runs roughly parallel to the break from one edge to the center of the tablet on this same side. There is a loss at one edge, a large portion of which has been re-attached with adhesive. There is another loss along an edge. Near this loss are some additional chip marks on the surface of the flat face. The convex face has some incomplete cracks. (Drawer 2)
  This advanced student exercise is an excerpt from Lipit-Eshtar's Praise in the Eduba (lines 54-55).
- School text, mathematical exercise of reciprocals., Early Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1800 BCE); SC-I-33; 2 3/4" height x 3" width x 13/16" depth, square tablet with the surfaces effaced; Square tablet with a crumbling and worn surface. Two edges and corners have losses. There seems to be some spalling in these areas. There are some grooves on the inscribed face that possibly were erasures made with an implement when the clay was still wet. There is a small chunk of an unknown black substance embedded in the body of the tablet near some of the losses -- possibly this was part of the makeup of the clay used for the tablet. There are some white concretions visible on parts of the surface. The clay is soft and actively crumbling. (Drawer 3)
  This is a student's practice using reciprocals and factors.
- School text, mathematical exercise of a multiplication table., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-II-10; 3 1/4" height x 2" width x 1" depth, rectangular single column tablet with the reverse uninscribed; Rectangular tablet made of light tan-colored clay. One face has losses at two corners on the same side. On the edge opposite the two broken corners there is a gouge from a modern (?) tool. There is a small chipped loss and a short crack in the middle of this face. The two broken corners are also visible on the opposite face. A third corner has a very small loss. One of the long sides has a deep hole or gouge near one of the intact corners. The interior of the hole is very uneven and does not appear to be made by an implement. (Drawer 4)
  This student exercise is a multiplication table based on 18.
- School text, sign exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-19; 1. To place 2. (Written) 9 times; 2 3/4" diameter x 13/16" depth, lentil joined from fragments; Disc-shaped tablet inscribed on one face only. The tablet has two large losses at the edge; the larger of the losses is also spalled on the inscribed face. There is a small, chipped loss at the edge that is more prominent on the uninscribed face. The uninscribed face has a long, diagonal scratch and small gouge running across center. This appears to be the result of a modern tool strike. (Drawer 5)
  This elementary exercise allowed the new scribe to practice forming the basic signs: GAR (to place) and BA (to distribute). Note the presence of a tally at the bottom of the tablet counting the total number of signs written on the tablet.
- School text, lexical exercise from Early Dynastic Lu A with pronunciation glosses., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 58; 4 1/4" height x 2 1/8" width x 7/8" depth, rectangular double column tablet with the reverse uninscribed; Tablet worked only on one face. The inscribed face has a shallow loss/abrasion at one corner. The clay on the inscribed face is pale greenish-gray in color, very different from most of the other tablets. One end of it is almost milky-white in color. The opposite face is heavily covered with a black residue, but it also has flecks of a bright white substance. There are two gashes to one side on this face. There is a a small gouge on the short side of the tablet close to these gashes. (Drawer 6)
  This basic exercise is a student's vocabulary practice in professions taken from the list Lu A. This student practice has glosses to assist the student in learning to pronounce the signs and words.
- School text, literary exercise from Lipit-Eshtar B., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-26; 5 1/2" height x 5 3/8" width x 1 7/8" depth, square multi-column fragment; A fragment of a large tablet. One face has a hole "drilled" toward one edge. This may be the work of boring insects. Along the same edge are three scraped lines that were most likely caused by metal tools during excavation. This face also has some fine cracks. The other face is heavily inscribed and has a triangular gouged loss on one edge. This gouge appears to have some adhesive in it, though there is no break there. The multiple layers of clay can be seen on the broken edges. These also show the rather crude original shape of the tablet. (Drawer S2)
  This tablet is an example of an advanced student's training. The obverse contains Lipit-Eshtar's Praise in the Eduba. The reverse has a unidentified literary composition.
- School text, administrative exercise of temple offerings., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); PARS 92; 7" height x 3 1/8" width x 1" depth, large rectangular double column tablet joined from fragments; The tablet is complete but one corner has been broken and reattached. The repair is poor; the two fragments are not properly matched. The clay of this tablet is unusually light in color but may be the result of firing conditions. There is a small loss to one of the corners adjacent to the repair and a smaller loss on the other adjacent corner. There are encrustations on both faces. (Drawer S3)
  This basic student exercise allowed the scribe to practice writing the lists of morning and evening provisions for Ninlil's second shrine. This text is a duplicate of 96287.
- School text, lexical exercise of wooden parts of the plow., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); 31719.15a-c; 1. The platform of the plow 2. The vessel of the plow 3. The … of the plow; 3" diameter x 13/16" depth, lentil joined from fragments with an adhesive label attached; Lenticular tablet that has broken into three pieces. These three pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. This clear adhesive is visible on the surface of the tablet along the breaks. There are losses long the breaks as well as two areas with losses along the edge that extend across the surface of the tablet, particularly on the inscribed face. There is a grooved gouge mark running across this same face, as if the clay was roughly scraped. It is difficult to tell if this was made while the clay was still wet or if it was made after the tablet had dried. There are a few incomplete cracks on the uninscribed face near a break and area with losses. There some white concretions visible, mostly on the inscribed face along a portion of the breaks and a portion of the losses around the breaks. There are some minor surface losses overall. Most of the tablet is tan-colored with some translucent black spots. Some portions of the tablet, mostly near the edges are a mottled cream color. This looks to be a thin layer of a white substance, possible a deposit (?). There is a small, cream-colored label with a typed number "15" that is adhered to the uninscribed face near an edge. (Drawer 1)
  This tablet contains a practice list of the wooden parts of the plow.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names beginning with "ib-ku"., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-18; 1. 'Kabta wept'; 2. 'Martu wept'; 3. 'Ishum wept'; 4. … 5. … 6. 'Urma wept'; 7. … 8. … 9. … 10. …; 5" height x 4 1/8" width x 1 1/8" depth, large rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet with a large loss to one corner and a smaller loss in another corner. There are a few minor losses to the surface of this face, including two small gashes that look to have been made when the clay was still wet. The convex face also has a few minor surface losses. One of the edges has six, shallow circular indentations, possibly made with an implement when the clay was still wet. There are small white concretions overall. (Drawer 2)
  This basic student exercise is practice writing personal names that begin with "ib". This acrographic arrangment was popular among ancient Mesopotamian vocabularies. Notice the mathematical calculations scribbled over lexical list on the reverse.
- School text, sign exercise from Syllable Alphabet A., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-II-1b; (Syllabary--no translation); 2 7/8" height x 2 5/8" width x 5/8" depth, square tablet joined from fragments with the reverse surface worn; The tablet has broken approximately in half and much of one corner has been lost. The broken portion that was not lost has been reattached with clear adhesive. There is an area of spalling on one face along this break. On one short side, a short crack is visible; this may actually be a second reattached break. There is a small area of loss along this crack/break. One face of the tablet is a very dark brown color, while the other face is gray-tan. (Drawer 3)
  This beginner's exercise is a practice in sign formation and sound. Notice the tablet rotation is left-to-right, not the typical top-to-bottom.
- School text, letter exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-1c; 3 7/8" height x 2" width x 1 3/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Tablet with a gouged loss, apparently from a modern (?) tool strike, near the corner of one face. Just below the gouge is an aread of partial loss, where part of the face has spalled. This damage is not visible on the opposite face. (Drawer 4)
  This student practice letter is from Sin-apulanni to Shamash-sharrashu, and refers to a previous letter.
- School text, literary exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-21; 1. From 'The true man'; 2. From Lu-si… 3. zi-garments to be cut.; 2 3/8" height x 3" width x 1 1/4" depth, lentil joined from fragments with the bottom face inscribed; Tablet that is mostly round, but with one disc-shaped edge. A chipped loss is missing from one edge. The tablet is inscribed on only one face. The inscribed face has several scattered cracks that are deep but incomplete. These cracks are over-filled with clear adhesive, so adhesive has bled onto the surface of the face. There is a small, chipped loss at center and another below a large patch of adhesive. The uninscribed face has a patch of adhesive at one edge covering a crack. The surface is uneven, with scattered chips and spots of spalling. (Drawer 5)
  This tablet is too damage to reconstruct the text written by a student. This small tablet was likely an excerpt from a piece of literature.
- School text, administrative exercise of month names., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); PARS 78; Obverse 1. Month 1: 'Shrine placed to the side'; 2. Month 2: 'The horned ox marches forth'; 3. Month 3: 'The brick'; 4. Month 4: 'To seed'; 5. Month 5: 'The lamps are lit'; 6. Month 6: 'The work of Inanna'; 7. Month 7: 'The shining mound'; 8. Month 8: 'The plow is released'; Reverse 1. Month 9: '…'; 2. Month 10: '…'; 3. Month 11: 'Emmer …'; 4. Month 12: 'Barley cutting'; 5. Month 13: '… barley cutting';; 2 3/8" height x 1 13/16" width x 3/4" depth, baked rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet with a loss at one corner. Marks at this corner indicate a modern tool created this loss. On one face, there is a gouge that looks like it was created with an implement. It is unclear if this gouge was formed when the clay was still wet, or if the damage occurred after firing. There are a few minor surface losses. A coating has been applied to the surface of the tablet. (Drawer 6)
  This basic student exercise allowed the scribe to practice writing the month names from the Nippur calendar. Each major city in the Ur III period had its own unique list and ordering of month names.
- School text, literary exercise from the Kesh Temple Hymn., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-40; 6 3/4" height x 3" width x 3 1/8" depth, square prism joined from fragments; This large, rectangular tablet is perforated with a 9/16" hole through its length. It has been broken into an unknown number of pieces and reassembled using a clear, shiny adhesive. The adhesive appears to have been applied to all cracks and breaks. The tablet is actively crumbling. Tiny detached bits can be found in the polyethelene bag. There appear to be deposits/encrustations, possibly salts, on one end and on the interiror of the perforation as well as on the large surface loss. In general, the repairs are poorly fit together and the object is extremely fragile. (Drawer S2)
  This advanced exercise is a complete edition of Kesh Temple Hymn. The earliest attestations of this hymn date back to the Early Dynastic Period (c. 2600-2350 BCE).
- School text, lexical exercise from ugu-mu., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-39a; 7 1/2" height x 5 1/4" width x 1 1/2" depth, large baked rectangular multi-column tablet joined from fragments; A fragment of a large tablet. The clay is poorly fired and fragile. One corner is broken and ready to detach (moves loosley). An adjacent corner has been reattached. One side of the tablet (of unknown size) is broken and lost. There are deep but incomplete cracks across one face. The opposite face has a few hairline cracks. Many tiny fragments have detached and are loose in the bottom of the poly bag. (Drawer S3)
  This tablet is a student's vocabulary practice writing various body parts from the standard Old Babylonian list.
- School text, mathematical exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-5; (Too broken to reconstruct); 3 1/2" diameter x 1 1/8" depth, lentil with the reverse inscribed; Lenticular tablet that appears to be stable. There are small losses to the surface of the convex face of the tablet. There are small, incomplete cracks that run throughout the flat face of the tablet. Adhesive has been applied to many of these cracks. There are deeps erasure marks on this same side, made when the clay was wet. There are very few cuneiform impressions visible on either side. There are a few small cream-colored concretions visible on the convex face. (Drawer 1)
  This math problem is largely erased and difficult to reconstruct.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-31; (Too broken to reconstruct); 4 1/16" height x 3 1/8" width x 9/16" depth, rectangular tablet joined from fragments with the reverse uninscribed; Rectangular tablet that has broken into two pieces. The two pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. There is a crevics between the two pieces along the entire break. This is due to losses along the break and possibly misalignment of the two pieces while being reattached. Adhesive is visible in portions of the break, and in one area is also on the surface near the break. There are losses to two corners as well as multiple losses to the surface of the tablet. It is difficult to tell whether or not the damage to the surface was done while the clay was still wet, or afterward because the patina is fairly consistent overall. There are some white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 2)
  This brief beginner's exercise only contains one line. Perhaps the student was interrupted before he could finish.
- School text, lexical exercise from Lu A., Uruk III (c. 3200-3000 BCE); SC-II-4a; Obverse Column 1 1. The yoke … 2. The travel official 3. … 4. … Column 2 1. … 2. The chief priest 3. The cattle pen attendant 4. … 5. The policeman Column 3 1. … 2. The chief 3. The chief … 4. The plowman 5. The chief Column 4 1. The chief … 2. … 3. The chief … 4. … 5. … Column 5 1. The chief … 2. … 3. The chief … 4. … 5. …; 3" height x 1 5/8" width x 1/2" depth, square multi-column fragment; Rectangular tablet fragment inscribed on one face only. On the inscribed face, one corner is damaged either by spalling or possibly a strike from a modern tool; this damage is a smooth, slanted loss. On the uninscribed face, one corner has a gouged loss that has removed part of the face without breaking off the whole depth of the corner. (Drawer 3)